<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Image Reconstruction on plundhammar</title>
    <link>https://plundhammar.github.io/tags/image-reconstruction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Image Reconstruction on plundhammar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.134.3</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:40:04 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://plundhammar.github.io/tags/image-reconstruction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the System Matrix and the LM-MLEM Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/understanding-the-system-matrix-and-the-lm-mlem-algorithm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:40:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/understanding-the-system-matrix-and-the-lm-mlem-algorithm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The List-Mode Maximum Likelihood Expectation Maximization (LM-MLEM) algorithm is widely used in Compton camera reconstruction. It&amp;rsquo;s well suited for the list-mode data architecture and easy to parallelize. This post will be somewhat technical and a sort of summary of the main arguments found in the litterature.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem has been stated many times, Ref.[1-8]. I will state it as follows (I will use the same notation as in Ref.[8]), and the proof of it will be the subject of a future post:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconvolution and the System Matrix</title>
      <link>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/deconvolution-and-system-matrices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:40:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/deconvolution-and-system-matrices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delving into the practicalities of the inverse problem of reconstructing Compton camera images will lead you to Legandre polynomials or Maximum Likelihood methods, most likely.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since last week I have been interested in both the analytical reconstruction techniques as well as some of the iterative methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding iterative methods, what I found is that it is difficult to get a feeling on how the iterative methods properly work simply because the algorithms (I write mine in Python) is increadibly slow. However, I have made some progress and have been able to reproduce some results but in a very corse voxel space. One way of simplifying things is to simplify the system matrix. I was reading Ref. [1] where they sort of reduce the forward problem to the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cone-Surface Projections</title>
      <link>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/cone-surface-projection-in-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 00:40:04 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://plundhammar.github.io/posts/cone-surface-projection-in-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the first properties encountered in Compton camera image reconstruction is the cone-surface projection. Understandig the properties of this geometrical object will set the ground works for understanding more advanced models.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading some articles of the early versions of the Compton camera image reconstruction procedure when I came across Ref.[1] talking about the &lt;em&gt;cone-surface projections&lt;/em&gt;. They investigated a primitive version of a &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;Compton camera&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;. Well, it kind of had some properties like a Compton camera like a scatterer and an absorber but they assumed that photons only scatter at a fixed given angle. This camera measures the cone-surface projection of a source. What this means is that the intensity measured at a given detector is proportional to the integral over the intersection of the cone and the source, given that the source is homogeneous.  Specifically, let $f(\mathbf{x})$ denote the source distribution, $\mathbf{k}$ the cone axis making angle $\beta$ with $\mathbf{n}$ along the cone surface, they defined&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
